[SPEAKER_00]: The meditation techniques popular today are not what the Buddha taught as mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the suttas do talk about the four foundations of mindfulness, mindfulness of the body and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: How should those practices be understood?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is their true purpose?
[SPEAKER_00]: And at which stage do they come into play?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look at the suttas themselves, when the Buddha talked about satipaṭṭhāna, they were taught to monks.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it clearly states there, after they would have already been practicing the gradual training thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even like the newly ordained monks would have been, would have given up sensuality, sexuality, eating at the wrong time, association, crowd with people, family, they would have given all of that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha told them the recollections of
[SPEAKER_01]: The four foundations of recollection, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And numerous suttas in, I think, Satipaṭṭhāna Sanyūtā, in Majjhima Nikāya as well, even add that, basically, after the monk is thoroughly established in virtue, upon virtue, on the basis of virtue, he practices these... how it's called.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's important because it's not, basically, it's not a...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a method that anybody can just pick up regardless of where their minds are at.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize that the whole training already begins through, as we said often, training in virtue and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, satipaṭṭhāna, the four foundations of recollections, would be just like a, say, a more unified form of training in that virtue, in that restraint that you would have already been training in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, on top of that, when the Buddha taught ānāpānasati, that was taught to people who were at least sotāpānas in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as a form of satipaṭṭhāna, ānāpānasati was even a more, say, specific way of development, that was pretty much for those that already had the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ānāpānasati sutta clearly states that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again,
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is not in you trying to do it, trying to understand what these practices are.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is taking them... Well, the problem is thinking that whatever idea you get about that practice, while being a non-sotāpanna, while being somebody who is not still established in virtue and gradual training and withdrawal from sensuality, you think that idea is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think that's what ānāpānasati is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think that's what satipaṭṭhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, through merely adhering to doing it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Mechanically, you will get where you need to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, it doesn't apply to you, which means you're not in a position to understand it until the prerequisites are met.
[SPEAKER_01]: Both satipaṭṭhāna and ānāpānasati sutta, it's not a meditation, it's certainly not a concentration practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a practice of non-forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, the name sati says that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Memory.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not forgetting the four reference points, whether you're sitting, walking, talking... Not forgetting it, because that means you're not forgetting the context of your situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not forgetting the context of your situation, well, it's a lot harder to become careless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a lot harder to make wrong choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Choices rooted in greed, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why virtue, establishment in virtue, basically, nearly like practicing towards sotāpārthi, and then becoming a sotāpārtha, is necessary for ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order to rightly
[SPEAKER_01]: If you recognize the choice of aversion or non-aversion, lust and non-lust, you would have needed to properly train in virtue for a sufficient amount of time, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: not choosing lust, aversion and distraction as a default.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it's not a negotiable basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, let me do this technique and then my virtue will develop as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, satipaṭṭhāna is already the result of virtue, the result of the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Furthermore, the reference point of citta, the third satipaṭṭhāna, again, Sotāpanna is the one that sees his citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody shorter than Sotāpanna sees their citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is nothing to apply to you there, because you don't have the necessary requirements.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than falling into a trap of, yeah, but, you know, everybody says, the entire Theravāda says, it's like, yeah, but what is that based on?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's based on Buddha's commentary and study monks from 10 centuries, 15 centuries ago, whenever it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was like 6,000 of them living at the monastery and just writing papers and translating Pali and recording stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not exactly a reference point for somebody who practices in seclusion, diligently in remote dwellings, for the dispassion and uprooting of all the kilesa.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the point is, like, restrain your tendency to to just accept that idea of a, like, shortcut, and start training in that which you can actually train.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it becomes a reference point, like your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what satipaṭṭhāna sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows mind affected with lust, there's mind affected with lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, actually, he directly sees the wild animal agitated with lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you would look at the animal, a lustful animal, or excited animal, or disturbed animal in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'd say, okay, that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it could cause me harm, it could make me sort of, you know, it will make me pay the price.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not my problem in that direct sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not me who is affected by this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see it clearly where it is, so I don't lose the sight of it, so that I don't pay the price.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, like, if you're practicing such right non-forgetfulness of the state of the animal, whatever that state of the animal is, Arahantship will be the the only possible outcome of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that means, at any given point, you know where the animal is and what it is doing, what state it is in, what feelings it is in, what intentions are evolving around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in and of itself, paired with the virtue that would have revealed the animal, paired with the right choices that would have outlined the whole satipaṭṭhāna practice, as in the four foundations that are there, whether you take them or not, they basically exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: You contemplating them rightly, in a sense of not concentrating on them as an object of your attention, but not completely forgetting about them either, letting them be on the peripheral,
[SPEAKER_01]: Letting it basically become a backdrop of your day-to-day choices, that is how you separate yourself from the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you disown it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you see... you see dhammas coming and going, you see citta changing, you see feelings coming and going, you see body being subjected to everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there will be no layer left for you to entertain any sense of ownership, if the practice of satipaṭṭhāna is successfully developed.